<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The act anent the setling of measures and weghts co[n]cluded at Edinburgh the 19 day of Februar 1618 yeeres. by the Co[m]missioners having power to doe the same by Act of Parliament made the twentie eight day of Iune 1617</title>
            <title>Laws, etc.</title>
            <author>Scotland.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1618</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 23 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 5 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A68706</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 21899</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S122309</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99857461</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99857461</idno>
            <idno type="VID">23202</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A68706)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 23202)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1430:10)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The act anent the setling of measures and weghts co[n]cluded at Edinburgh the 19 day of Februar 1618 yeeres. by the Co[m]missioners having power to doe the same by Act of Parliament made the twentie eight day of Iune 1617</title>
                  <title>Laws, etc.</title>
                  <author>Scotland.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>21-24 leaves   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Thomas Finlason,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[Edinburgh :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1618]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Caption title; at head of page: God, and my right in my defence.</note>
                  <note>Imprint from STC.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: L-M² .</note>
                  <note>A supplement to STC 21898.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the New York Public Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Weights and measures --  Scotland --  Law and legislation --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-05</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-05</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-07</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-07</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="21" facs="tcp:23202:1"/>
            <head>GOD, AND MY RIGHT JN MY DEFENCE. THE ACT ANENT THE SETLING of Meaſures and Weghts, co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cluded at <hi>Edinburgh</hi> the 19 day of Februar 1618 yeeres. by the Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>misſioners having power to doe the ſame by Act of Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment made the twentie eight day of Iune 1617</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">F</seg>Orſomuch as in Our Soveraine Lords laite Parliament holden at <hi>Edinburgh,</hi> the xxviij day of June laſt bypaſt his Highnes and Eſtates conveined therein, Mooved by the generall complaint of all his louing Sub<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>jects: and in reſpect of their ſenſible prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>judice ſeene and felt through many parts of this Kingdome by reaſon of the diverſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie of Meaſures and Weghts uſed within the ſame.</p>
            <p>Therefore Our ſaid Soveraine Lord, with adviſe of his ſaids Eſtates; For removing of all abuſes which may enſue in any tyme to come, thereby hath found expedient and by Decreet &amp; Statute of the ſaid Parliament; Decerned, Statut, and Ordeined, That there ſhall bee but one juſt Meaſure and Weght, through all the partes of this Kingdome; which ſhall Univerſallie ſerve all his Highnes Leiges by the which they ſhall buy, ſell, receiue, and giue out, in all tyme to come. Which Meaſure his Majeſtie with adviſe foreſaid, Fand; ſhould be that Meaſure of <hi>Linlithgo,</hi> which is now commonlie uſed and which hath beine uſed moſt cuſtomablie through the greateſt part of this Kingdome theſe fiftie or thrieſcore yeeres bypaſt. And for ſetling of a perfyte order whereby all the Meaſures that are now uſed may be reduced to the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formitie of the ſaid meaſure now authorized, and for making of propor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion anſwerable betwix the Leſſer Meaſurs and Weghts, and the Greateſt.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:23202:2"/>
            <p>His MAJESTIE with adviſe foreſaid, granted full power and Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion, To S<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
               <hi>Iames Weemes</hi> of Bogie knight. S<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
               <hi>George Auchinlek</hi> of Bal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manno knight. S<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
               <hi>Iames Fowles</hi> of Colingtoun knight. S<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
               <hi>Robert Stewart</hi> of Shillinglaw knight. S<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
               <hi>Ihone Waws</hi> of Barnbarro knight. S<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
               <hi>William Greir<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſon</hi> of Lag knight. And to <hi>Iames Nisbet</hi> Bailyie and burges of <hi>Edinburgh,</hi> M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
               <hi>Allex<hi rend="sup">t</hi> Wedderburne</hi> Clerk of Dondie. S<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
               <hi>Thomas Menzeis</hi> Proveſt of Aberdeine. <hi>Iames Hamilton</hi> Proveſt of Glaſgow. <hi>Iohn Oisburne</hi> burges of Aire and S<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
               <hi>George Bruce</hi> of Carnok knight. burges of Culros. Whome or any eight of them, His Majeſtie with adviſe foreſaid, Ordeined to meet and conveine together, at ſuch tyme and place as they ſhould think ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pedient. And to conſult and adviſe together, and to appoint and deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine vpon the moſt convenient meanes how the ſaids Meaſures and Weghts, might bee reduced to the conformitie foreſaid. As in the ſaid laite Act of Parliament at more length is conteined.</p>
            <p>Which whole Commiſſioners foreſaids, hauing mett and conveined with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in the Burgh of <hi>Edinburgh</hi> vpon the twentie ane day of Januar laſt bypaſt and the moſt part of them vpon diuers and ſunrie others dayes thereafter in the ſaid moneth of Januar and Februar inſtant. And hauing read and conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered the foreſaid Act of Parliamet, anent the ſaids meaſures and Weghts and finding that It is Ordeined that their ſhall be onlie Ane juſt Meaſure and Weght, through all the parts of this Realme which ſhall vniverſallie ſerve all his Maieſties Leiges (by the which and no other) they ſhall buy and ſell, in all tyme comming. And that it is declared by the ſaid Act that the foreſaid Meaſure and Firlot of <hi>Linlithgo</hi> which is now commonlie vſed and which hath bene moſt cuſtomablie vſed through the greateſt part of this Kingdome theſe fiftie or thrie ſcore yeeres bygone, ſhalbe the foreſaid juſt Meaſur and Firlot which ſhall be receiued and vſed by all his Majeſties Lie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges in all tyme co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ming. And that Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>miſſion is giuen bee vertue of the ſaid Act to the ſaids Commiſſioners for ſetling of a perfect order whereby all the ſaids Meaſures that are now vſed, may be reduced to the conformitie of the ſaid meaſure of <hi>Linlithgo.</hi> And for making of a proportion betwixt the leſſer meaſures and weghts and the greateſt. Haue firſt thoght it meit and expedient that the Proveſt and Baillyes of <hi>Linlithgo</hi> who are keepers of the ſaid meaſure ſhuld produce before them the ſaid meaſure which hath bene given owt be them to the Burrows and all others his Majeſties Leiges theſe fiftie or thrie-ſcore yeeres bygone, with their Jedges and warrands which they haue for the ſame. Who being cited for that effect, Produced before the ſaids Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>miſſioners their ſaid Meaſure and Firlot with the Jedge which is their warrand thereof. And the ſame meaſure and firlot being fund agreable with the ſaid Jedge, the ſaids Commiſſioners cauſed praeſentlie fill the ſame with water which being full, they fand that the ſame coteined Twentie ane pincts and ane mutchkin of juſt <hi>Sterline</hi> Jug and meaſure, and that the foreſaid jug containes within the ſame Thrie punds and ſeaven vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of frenſh Troys weght, of clear runing water of the water of <hi>Leith.</hi> And becauſe the ſaids Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>miſſioners could find out no other meane whereby they might trye the warra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d of the Quantitie of the ſaid meaſure and firlot of <hi>Lin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lithgo</hi> which hath bene in vſe theſe fiftie or thrie-ſcore yeeres bygone. But be taking of the oaths of the ſaids Proveſt and Baillyes thereanent. They
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:23202:2"/> tooke the oathes of <hi>Andro Milne</hi> Proveſt of the ſaide Burgh of <hi>Linlithgo Andro Bell</hi> and <hi>Iames Glen</hi> Baillyes thereof who being with all requiſite Solemnitie Sworne: Deponed vpon their conſciences; That the foreſaid Fir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lot and Meaſure produced by them, was the verie true and Juſt meaſure which hath bene given owt to his Majeſties Leiges by them and their prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diceſſors theſe fiftie or thrie-ſcore yeeres by gone, and that the ſame by their knowledge hath never been altered in any ſort during the tyme foreſaid, and ſiklike declared vpon their conſciences, that ſo far as they could trye by the moſt ancient and aged perſons of their Burgh, that the foreſaids Jedges are of great antiquitie and haue neuer bene altered or changed in any tyme by<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gone: And that they never had, nor hes, any other Meaſure, or Iedge to their knowledge.</p>
            <p>Which Firlot, the ſaids Commiſſioners Haue Fund, and Declared, Sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tute and Ordeided, to be the Juſt and onlie Firlot which ſhall be received and uſed, by all his Majeſties Lieges in all tyme comming: For metting of Wheat, Rye, Beines, Peas, Meal, Whyt Salt, and ſuch other ſtuff &amp; Victuall as before this tyme hath beine in Uſe to bee meaſured by ſtraik Mett, within this Kingdome. The wydnes, and Breadnes, of the which Firlot vnder and above euen over within the buirds, ſhall contein nyne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teen Inches, and ſext part inche; and the deipnes, ſeaven Inches, and ane thrid part of ane inche: and the Peck, halfe Peck, and fourt part Peck to bee made effeirand thereto; And the ſteppes of the ſaid Firlot to be in thiknes one Inche at the leaſt: That the Bottome thereof bee croſſed with Iron nayled to the ſame, and to the Ring of the Firlot; and the edge of the bottome entring within the lagene bee pared outwith towards the nether-ſyde, and to be made in with plaine and juſt reul-right; That the mouth bee ringed about with ane croce or girth of Iron inwith and out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with, hauing a croce Iron barre paſſing ouer from the one ſyde to the other thrie ſquared, and edge doun, and a plaine ſyde vp, which ſhall goe reul-right with the edge of the Firlot, and euerie ſquare ſhall be ane juſt Inche of breadth. And that there be ane prick of Iron one Inche in roundnes, with ane ſhoulder vnder and aboue and ryſing vpright out of the Centre or midſt of the bottome of the Firlot, and paſſing through the midſt of the ſaid over croce-barre, rooved both vnder and aboue.</p>
            <p>And that the ſaid Cowpar cauſe the ring-ſtraik of the ſaid Firlot, paſſe from the one end of the ſaid over Iron barre to the other: And the ſame to bee brunt and ſealled, with the mark of foure Crownes, vpon both the ſydes of the bottome, with fyve impreſſions of the letter L vpon the lippes thereof. And for eſchuing of fraud in all tyme comming; The ſaids Commiſſioners all in one voice but diſcrepance or variance, Haue tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ught expedient Statut and Ordeined, by vertue of the foreſaid Commi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſſion granted to them by the ſaid laite Act of Parliament, That all Vic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall and ſtuff ſhall bee meaſured by ſtraik, through all the parts of this Kingdome, in all tyme comming. And by reaſon that Mault, Beare, and Aites, haue euer beene uſed to bee meaſured by heape; and that by the meaning of ſeverall praeceiding Acts of Parliament, IT hath beine tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ught, that Heapes in proportion was the juſt thrid of the Firlot and Peck, So that thrie ſtraiked Firlots, for two heaped Firlots, Sex ſtraiked Firlots
<pb facs="tcp:23202:3"/> for foure heaped Firlots, was thought to bee a juſt proportion, the one agreable to the other. And the ſaids Commiſſioners by tryall and exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mination hauing found that the Heape in proportion, IS not the juſt thrid part of the Firlot and Peck, but that there is a great difference therein, and no ſmall praejudice both to the giver and receiver, of thrie ſtraiked Firlots or Pecks, for two heaped firlots or pecks, and conſequentlie of ſex for foure, the Heape being alwayes the leſſe meaſure as ſaid is.</p>
            <p>THEREFORE they haue found it expedient to cauſe make ane particular Meaſure or Firlot, for metting of Mault, Beare, and Aites, by ſtraike, in all tyme comming, which being made and produced in their preſence, and after tryall and examination thereof, Haue found the ſame in proportion neireſt to the ſaid Heape, ſo that foure ſtraiked Meaſures or Firlots thereof, conteines in juſt proportion (and to the leſſe praeju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dice of all his Majeſties Lieges) foure heaped Firlots. Which the ſaids Commiſſioners hauing cauſed fill with cleare running water of the wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of <hi>Leith,</hi> They find the ſame to conteine Thrittie one Pincts, of the juſt <hi>Sterline</hi> Jugge and meaſure, ilk Pinct conteining the Weght fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid. And the ſame to bee in wydnes and breadnes aequall and conforme to the former Firlot, and in deipnes, Ten Inches and ane halfe inche.</p>
            <p>Which they Find, Statute and Ordeins, To remaine as ane juſt Mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure and Firlot, to bee Uſed for metting and meaſuring of Mault, Beare, and Aittes, by ſtraike, in all tyme comming. And that the Pecks, halfe Pecks, and fourt part Pecks thereof bee made conforme in proportione to the ſame laſt Firlot: Which new Firlot in all other reſpects ſhall be agreable in forme with the old ſtraike Firlot aboue written, having one Iron girth more in the midſt thereof outwith, and marked with the im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſion of the letter H. on the outmoſt ſyds thereof.</p>
            <p>And the ſame with the foreſaid other Firlot conteining twentie ane pincts &amp; ane mutchkin, To bee giuen out by the ſaids Proveſt and Baillyes of <hi>Linlihgow,</hi> to whoſe cuſtodie the ſame was co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mitted of old, To the Bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowes and all others his Majeſties Lieges for that effect, betwix the date hereof and the twentie day of Apryle next-to come. And that foure fulles of either of the foreſaids Firlots conteine and bee repute to bee ane juſt BOLL, in all tyme co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ming allenerlie. Siclyke the ſaids Commiſſioners hauing conſidered the great Praejudice ſuſteined by all OUR Soveraine LORDS Lieges through the diverſitie of Weghts, uſed within all the parts of this Realme.</p>
            <p>THERFORE and conforme to their ſaid Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>miſſion and Act of Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament foreſaid, and for eſchuing of all fraud, Haue thought expedient, Statute, and Ordeined, That there ſhall bee onely one Juſt Weght thr<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ough all the parts of this Kingdome, which ſhall Univerſallie ſerue all his Majeſties Lieges (by the which and no other) they ſhall buy and ſell, all and whatſomever Wares accuſtomed to be boght and ſauld by Weght als weell Foraine, as Cuntrie-Wares; in all tyme hereafter: to wit, The frenſh Troys Stone Weght, conteining Sexteine Troys Pounds, in the Stone, and Sexteine Troys Unces in the Pound, and the leſſer Weghts and Meaſures to be made in proportio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> conforme therto: (And that Weght called of old the Trone weght to bee allvtterlie aboliſhed and diſharged,
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:23202:3"/> and neuer hereafter to bee received nor vſed.) And in reſpect that the keiping and out-giuing of the Weghts of old to the Burrowes, and others his Majeſties Lieges within this Kingdome; was co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mitted to the Burgh, of <hi>Lanerk:</hi> Therefore the ſaids Commiſſioners haue committed the kee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping and out-giuing of the ſaid frenſh Troys Stone Weght, now eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſhed, to the foreſaid Burgh of <hi>Lanerk</hi> and their Succeſſors, to be gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven out by them and their ſaids ſucceſſors to the Burrowes and others his Majeſties Lieges, betwix the date hereof and the Firſt day of Maij next to come, and in all tyme comming.</p>
            <p>And lykewayes Statuts and Ordeins, that there bee double Standards of the foreſaids Firlots and Meaſures, and Jedges thereof, and of the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaids Weghts, Two of euerie one of them to remaine in the Regiſter, within the Caſtell of <hi>Edinburgh,</hi> and other two within the Caſtell of <hi>Dun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>britane,</hi> therein to remaine as a warrand for the meaſures allenerlie. And the other in the Townes to whom they haue beine co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mitted of old as ſaid is, to be direct foorth to the whole Lieges to be vſed Univerſalie. And this with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out praejudice to any perſons who are founded infeft or addetted, by Tak or contract, of old or new fermes of others Meaſures and Weghts; but that their Foundation, Infeftment, Tack, or Contract, ſhall bee propor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned to the Meaſure and Weght now eſtabliſhed, ſo that the ſame qua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titie ſhall remaine with the giuer and receiuer, but praeiudice to any of them. Sicklyke haue found and declared, That the Elne and Stand ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of committed to the keiping of the Burgh of <hi>Edinburgh,</hi> conteineth Thrit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie ſeven Inches. And the Pinct Stowp, co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mitted to the keiping of ye Burgh of <hi>Sterline,</hi> conteineth the weght of Thrie Pounds ſeaven Unces of frenſh Troys weght cleare ru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ning water of the watter of <hi>Leith.</hi> Which Elne, and Stowp, They Statut and Ordaine, to remaine and abyde in the ſame in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tegritie as they are now, and that no other Elne nor Stowp, or greater or leſſe proportion conteining the ſaid weght, ſhall bee receiued by none of his Majeſties Leiges in any tyme comming, to buy or ſell with; in any part of this Kingdome. And the halfe and quarter Elnes, and halfe quarters, and Nails: Quart, Chopin, Mutchkin, and halfe mutchkine Stowps, bee made in proportion conforme thereto. And the Burghes of <hi>Edinburgh,</hi> and <hi>Sterline,</hi> to whome the keiping thereof hath beine com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted of old; haue the out-giuing of the ſame to the reſt of the Burrous and all others his Majeſties Lieges to that effect, betwixt and the Firſt day of Apryle next to come: And that they haue dowble Standards of the ſaids Elne, and Stowp, Two of euerie one of them, To remaine in the Regiſter within the Caſtell of <hi>Edinburgh,</hi> and within the Caſtell of <hi>Dunbritane,</hi> for a warrand as ſaid is: and the other with themſelfes and their ſucceſſors, to whome they haue beine committed of old: And that the foreſaids Meaſures, Mets, and Weghts, with the which all and what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſomeuer perſons ſhall bee holden to buy, ſell, mett, meaſure, wegh, and deliuer, haue courſe allenerlie within this Realme; after the dayes reſp<hi rend="sup">•</hi> after following viz. The Weghts after the Firſt day of May next to com and the Meaſures of Firlots and Pecks, and the reſt of that degrie, after the Firſt day of June next thereafter, and no other Weghts, Metts, nor Meaſures, to bee received nor vſed in any tyme hereafter; in any part
<pb facs="tcp:23202:4"/> of this Kingdome, vnder the paines contained in the Acts of Parliament made thereanent: and that all Firlots to be vſed in Markets both to burgh and Land be brunt and ſealed either with the marks and Sealls of <hi>Lin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lithgo</hi> in maner foreſaid, or with the burning Iron of the head burgh of the ſhyre wherein the ſaids markets are holden, And that the Proveſt and Baillyes of Royall Burrowes, and Cities both Regalitie and Royaltie, &amp; als the Baillyes of Burrowes in Baronnie, and Juſtices of Peace in what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſomeuer places where markets of Victuall are holden, or others Foraine or Cuntrie Wares ſhall be boght, ſauld, and weghed, mett, and meaſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, ſhall be bound, That all meaſures and weghts to be vſed ſhall bee of one forme and quantitie, according to this preſent Act: And if any different meaſures and weghts be found in any of the places aboue men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned. The ſaids Proveſt and Baillyes of Royalties, Regalities, Baronies and Juſtices of Peace; ſhall take order therewith and if need be ſhalbe holden to informe the Kings Majeſties Counſell thereof, that they may take order thereanent as appertaineth.</p>
            <p>Provyding alwayes as is before provyded, if any perſons bee founded or infeft, and adetted by Tak, or contract, of old or new Ferme, of mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures and weghts, then are before written in maner foreſaid. Their foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation Tack or Contract, whether it be more or leſſe, ſhall be propor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned to this meaſure and weght which now is eſtabliſhed, ſo that the ſame quantitie ſhall remaine with the giver and receiver, but prejudice to any of them in maner particularlie before expreſſed. And becauſe by the Proviſions immediatlie before written, divers Pleyes and queſtions, may aryſe bewix parties, receivers and deliverers, Maiſters and tenents Fewers and their Superiors, anent Fermes and Victuall, and ſiclyk ane<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t other ſtuff and dueties, adetted and bound to be payed and delivered by weght, either by infeftments, Tacks, foundations, bandes, or contracts whatſomeuer, made before the date hereof anent the conforming and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portionating of the meaſures and weghts conteined in the ſaids infeftme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts Tacks foundations and others Securities foreſaids, with the meaſures &amp; Weghts now eſtabliſhed, if ſure notice and tryall be not taken of the juſt meaſure and quantitie of the meaſures and weghts which haue beine moſt cuſtomablie vſed and received theſe fiftie or thrieſcore yeeres bygone, within the Shirefdomes vnder-written, viz. <hi>Lanerk, Wigtoun, Drumfreis, Roxburgh,</hi> and <hi>Bervik.</hi> In the which the ſaids Commiſſioners conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring evidentlie the greateſt diverſitie of meaſures and weghts, from the meaſures and weghts now eſtabliſhed, to bee for the moſt part: So that theſe fyve ſhyres being broght to the conformitie aforeſaid, the reſt of the Shyres within this Kingdome may be eaſilie reduced to the ſame, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forme to this preſent Act.</p>
            <p>THEREFORE the ſaids Commiſſioners, Finds it meet and expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dient, and by theſe preſents Statuts, Decernes, and Ordeins, That the Shiref of everie one of the foreſaids fyve ſhyres of <hi>Lanerk, Wigtoun, Dru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>freis, Roxburgh,</hi> and <hi>Bervik;</hi> or their Deputs ſhall warne the Baillyes of Regalities within the ſame Shyres, and Steuarts of Steuartries thereof, if any bee, Juſtices of Peace, and Magiſtrates of Burrowes, To convein ilk one them within the heade Bourgh of the ſame Shyre wherein they
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:23202:4"/> are Magiſtrates, within twentie dayes after the Counſels pleaſure ſhall be ſignified to them thereanent: and there not onlie to receiue and em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brace the ſaids meaſurs and weghts, from the Proveſt &amp; baillyes of <hi>Linlithgo</hi> &amp; <hi>Lanerk,</hi> to whome the keiping thereof is concredit in maner foreſaid, &amp; which are eſtabliſhed by this preſent Act: But alſo to take tryall and cog<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nition of the difference betwix the ſaids old meaſures and weghts, and the meaſures and weghts now eſtabliſhed. And to appoint conclude &amp; determine, ilkone of them within their owne bounds, what proportion leſſe or more ſhall bee giuen and received in tyme comming, for con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forming of their Fermes and dueties adetted by former infeftments, fon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dations, Tacks, contracts, bands and Securities: to the foreſaids Mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures and Weghts now eſtabliſhed, and to inſert the ſame in their Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſters and Court books; To remaine with them for deciſioun of ſuch controverſies as may aryſe in thoſe bounds hereafter, anent the diſcon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formitie foreſaid: and to report their diligence thereanent and conclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion in writte authenticklie ſubſcryved by the ſaids Shirefs of Shyres, Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrats of Royall Burrowes, Baillyes of Regalities, Burghs of Baronnies, and Juſtices of Peace; conveining within ilkane of the foreſaids Shir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>refdomes: And to preſent the ſame to the Lords of his Majeſties Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſell and Seſſion, before the firſt day of Julie next-to come; To the effect the ſame may bee delyvered to the Clerke of Regiſter to bee inſert in the bookes of Counſell <hi>(ad futuram rei memoriam.)</hi> And that none of the foreſaids fyve ſhyres, nor no others his Majeſties Lieges within this Kingdome, praeſume nor tak vpon hand in tyme to come; To buy, Sell, blok bargane, contract, or ſett in Tack, to, or with others, for receipt or delyverie, with any other Weght, Mett, or Meaſure, nor the ſame which now by this preſent Act is approoved and eſtabliſhed. And this for re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port of the Commiſſion aboue written, Requyring the Lords of Our So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veraine LORDS Counſell and Seſſion, That Letters may bee direct for publication of the praemiſſes by oppen Proclamation at the market Croces of the head Burrowes of this Realme, and others places neidfull that none praetend ignorance of the ſame, Commanding and charging, all and ſundrie the ſaids Proveſts and Baillyes of Burrowes and Citties, both of Royaltie and Regalitie, and alſo the Baillyes of Burrowes in Baronnies, Juſtices of Peace, and others whatſomeuer, in places where markets are holden; To put in execution this praeſent Act and euerie part thereof in ſo farre as concerneth them, ſo that the ſame may take full effect after the dayes reſp<hi rend="sup">ue</hi> foreſaids: With certification to them &amp; they faillye, they ſhall be called and accuſed, and the paines conteined in the Acts of Parliament, ſhall bee execute vpon them in all rigour in example of others. In witneſſing of the which the ſaids Cammiſſioners haue ſubſcryved theſe praeſents with their hands, Day, Yeere, and Place foreſaids. And Ordeins theſe praeſents to bee delyvered to the Clerke of Regiſter, to the effect hee may cauſe inſert the ſame in the Regiſter of Parliament.</p>
            <figure>
               <q>MEDIOCRIA ⚜ FIRMA</q>
            </figure>
            <pb facs="tcp:23202:5"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
